<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sheba's conspiracy and Amasa's confederacy, or, A modest vindication of the national association entred into by the Honorable House of Commons, Feb. 25th, 1695 being a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of St. James Clarkenwell, March 29th / by D. Pead ...</title>
            <author>Pead, Deuel, d. 1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11952385</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11952385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 38:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sheba's conspiracy and Amasa's confederacy, or, A modest vindication of the national association entred into by the Honorable House of Commons, Feb. 25th, 1695 being a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of St. James Clarkenwell, March 29th / by D. Pead ...</title>
                  <author>Pead, Deuel, d. 1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51468:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SHEBA</hi>'s CONSPIRACY, AND <hi>AMASA</hi>'s CONFEDERACY: OR, A Modeſt VINDICATION OF THE <hi>National Aſſociation <hi>Entred into by the</hi>
               </hi> Honorable Houſe of Commons <hi>Feb.</hi> 25<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. 1695.</p>
            <p>BEING A SERMON Preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>James Clarkenwell,</hi> March 29th.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. PEAD,</hi> Chaplain to his Grace <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>New-Caſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51468:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51468:2"/>
            <head>To his Moſt Sacred Majeſty William the III.</head>
            <head type="sub">OF <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Grace of God, Rightful and Lawful King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Gracious Sovereign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>VAlens</hi> the Emperor having incautelouſly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the pernicious Errors of <hi>Arius,</hi> in a ſhort time great part of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> became infected with the ſame Principles: In thoſe Days <hi>Aphrates</hi> the Monk, leaving his Cell, appeared in Publick, ſtriving by his Art and Wit to oppoſe that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Torrent; and to ſuch as thought him too forward, he offered no other Apology, than that the Neceſſity of the Times forced him from his Retirement. Our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable Enemies of <hi>Rome,</hi> who have for many Years laboured the Deſtruction of our Church and Nation, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Hands too feeble to effect their Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, have at laſt by a ſubtle Stratagem brought over too many of Ours to their Aſſiſtance; for having cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly inveigled with ſome to preſs the Doctrine of <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience,</hi> in a time unſeaſonable, and in a Cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:51468:3"/>not requiring, Men's Affections became much alienate from the Truth they fear'd would expoſe 'em; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving prevailed on others to invalidate your Majeſty's Juſt and Legal Title to the Crown, by introducing an uncouth Notion of a King <hi>de Facto,</hi> by which Doctrine they have brought ſome to believe, that Rebellion againſt a Prince no better qualified, was neceſſary, just, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable as well to God as Man; in which Opinion ſome have already perſiſted unto Death. At ſuch a time to be ſilent, is to be inſenſible; not to reprove, is to encourage; and not to oppoſe ſuch irreligious Principles and Practiſes, is to want not only Loyalty but Religion. The chief Deſigns of this Diſcourſe, now humbly laid at your Majeſty's Feet, are to confirm ſuch, as have hitherto kept themſelves uncorrupted, in Loyalty and Obedience to your Majeſty, to reclaim if poſſible ſome of the fallen; as for the more froward and obſtinate, they muſt be left to your Majeſty's Juſtice; which I hope that God, who hath ſo miraculouſly preſerved and defended you, will direct and enable you ſo to execute, that it may be ſeen to the Comfort of the Loyal and the Terror of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, that your Majeſty bears not the Sword in vain.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant your Majeſty a long Life, that you may at laſt behold and rejoice in the Travel of your Soul, the Preſervation, Reformation, and Proſperity of your Kingdoms: And let all the People ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Which is the Conſtant Prayer of <hi>Your MAJESTY's moſt Loyal, Moſt Obedient, and Moſt Humble Subject,</hi> Deuel Pead.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51468:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE <hi>National Aſſociation.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Sam. XX. 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And there hap'ned to be there a man of Belial, whoſe name was Sheba, the ſon of Bichri, a Benjamite; and he blew a trumpet, and ſaid, we have no part in David, neither have we inheritance in the ſon of Jeſſe: every man to his tents O Iſrael.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>GOD, whoſe only Prerogative it is, ever hath been, and ſhall be, to diſpoſe of Kingdoms, was pleaſed to Appoint and Anoint <hi>David</hi> the Son of <hi>Jeſſe</hi> to wear <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Crown; not that he delighted in Changes and Innovation; but his Wiſdom and Juſtice could not bear that ſuch as reigned only by his Comimſſion, ſhould diſpute or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51468:4"/>his Commands: Wherefore <hi>Saul</hi> forgetting his Duty both to God and his People, God ſaw it high time to remove him, and made room for the Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Prince who ſhould prove more willing and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; yet though this was apparently the Lord's Doings, all were not then, (no more than they are now) ſatisfy'd therewith. Some turbulent Spirits lay upon the Catch, watching the Opportunity of a Revolution; theſe reſolved that ſeeing God had tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated the Diadem from the Tribe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> to that of <hi>Judah,</hi> they would either bring it back, or elſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Monarchy into a Commonwealth, of which number was <hi>Sheba,</hi> who took Pett at the Honour the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> had done themſelves in being ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous (after the Defeat of <hi>Abſalom</hi>) to conduct <hi>David</hi> from <hi>Mahanaim</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for if you conſult the 41 Verſe of the preceding Chapter, you will find the Ten Tribes ſharply conteſting with the Men of <hi>Judah,</hi> and blaming them for their ſo great haſte in tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the King and his Houſhold, without calling them to the Conſult, that they alſo might have ſhared in the Honour of ſuch a Loyal Action; who, hearing this, would not have concluded <hi>David</hi> exceeding happy in the Affection of his Subjects? But <hi>All is not Gold that gliſters:</hi> All are not therefore loyal, becauſe at this Juncture of Time (upon the Diſcovery of ſo horrid a Plot) they have ſet their Hands to an Aſſociation: for even thoſe Men who were ſo hot in the Contention, pretending ſo much Loyalty of a ſudden, in the Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of <hi>Abſalom</hi> deſerted <hi>David</hi>'s Standard; and, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few Minutes, you will find them cloſing with <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba</hi>'s Traiterous Counſel. And, as ſaith the Verſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Text, they forſook <hi>David;</hi> and I fear ſome, who are now very forward in theſe Demonſtrations of Loyalty, (had the Enemy landed) would have held it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51468:4"/>their beſt Policy to have met him, in an obſequious manner, thereby to ſave their Eſtates. It is pity ſuch have any to ſave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sheba</hi> being among theſe diſcontented Perſons, and perceiving them in a Ferment, cloſed with the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity; and, to blow them up into a Flame, he blew a Trumpet, and ſaid, <hi>We have no part in David, neither have we inheritance in the ſon of Jeſſe: every man to his tents O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conſider theſe Words after this Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I ſhall treat of the Perſon: <hi>Sheba the ſon of Bichri, a Benjamite;</hi> and, which we muſt not forget, <hi>a Man of Belial.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. His Action: <hi>He blew a Trumpet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. His Speech: <hi>And ſaid, we have no part in Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, neither have we Inheritance in the Son of Jeſſe: every Man to his Tents O Iſrael.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe Things diſpatch'd, I ſhall conclude with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Counſel,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon: Of whom I ſhall not ſpeak much; and that for two Reaſons; the one becauſe I find no Good to relate of him; the other, becauſe the leſs we have to do with ſuch Perſons, the better.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By his Behaviour: A Man of <hi>Belial; i. e.</hi> a yokeleſs, lawleſs Perſon, a peſtilent Fellow, a Mover of Sedition, a meer <hi>Salamander,</hi> that would expire, were it not for the Fire of Contention; a very Child of the Devil. One would think no wiſe Perſons would come at ſuch a ones Call, or find leiſure to hear his Speeches; yet ſome have ſuch itching Ears, that they will liſten to any Villain that knows how to ſpeak Treaſon enough.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:51468:5"/>
Secondly, He is deſcribed by his Name, <hi>Sheba;</hi> (which being interpreted) implies Captivity or Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage; and this Man was really, <hi>Vir ſui nominis,</hi> one that anſwered his Name to a Title; for had <hi>Iſrael</hi> adher'd to his Advice, they had as certainly been made Slaves to the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> as we to the <hi>French,</hi> if we had all (as ſome did lately) deſerted King <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, He is deſcrib'd by his Family or Tribe, he was Son of <hi>Bichri,</hi> a <hi>Benjamite; i. e,</hi> one that could not brook to ſee the Crown ſettled in the Tribe of of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſidering the many Provocations of the <hi>Jews,</hi> it was a Mercy that God would permit them a King of their own Blood and Nation, whereas in Juſtice he might have given way that ſuch as hated them ſhould have held them in Subjection; yet inſtead of a grateful Acknowledgment of God's Loving Kindneſs, we meet with a murmuring againſt his Providence; and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfy'd are theſe <hi>Benjamites,</hi> that if they may not have a King of their own Tribe, they care for no King; of like mind are the Papiſts, and their wicked Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices, if they cannot have a King of their own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion and Temper, no other ſhall live in Safety or Peace.</p>
            <p>I paſs from the Perſon to his Action.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Action: <hi>He blew a Trumpet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some whiſper Treaſon, and are well ſatisfied in dark holes to plot bloody Miſchiefs, hoping no eye ſhall ſee them; but here we have a Traitor in Grain, that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not who hears him; nay, takes care to be heard; for leſt he ſhould not have Auditors enough, he ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons them with a Trumpet: When Rebellion, War, and Blood was the Banquet, a Trumpet was a fit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to congregate the Gueſts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51468:5"/>
Treaſon is bad enough when conceal'd and ſolitary, when it is promoted in Cabals, and tranſmitted by Cabaliſtical Letters; but it is come to its heighth, when it dare appear bare-fac'd; when <hi>Sheba</hi> with his Trumpet and Tongue ſhall loudly and openly, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and publickly proclaim himſelf a Traitor, and invite others into the Conſpiracy.</p>
            <p>Too many among us have ſounded ſuch Trumpets; nay, they that ought to have known better, and taught better, have from their Pulpits trumpeted, <hi>We have no part in David, neither have we inheritance in the ſon of Jeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us obſerve (though never believe) his Speech: <hi>We have no part in David, nor inheritance in in the ſon of Jeſse: To your tents O Iſrael.</hi> Here is a Speech made up of Lye, Slander, and Treaſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Lye in theſe Words: <hi>We have no part in David. Solomon</hi>'s Obſervation is, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Fools ſeek to hide their hatred with lying lips;</hi> ſo that <hi>Sheba</hi> hath at once proclaim'd himſelf Lyar and Fool: What no part in <hi>David,?</hi> Can he be a good Subject, and have no Intereſt in a good King? Out of thy own Mouth we will judge this wicked Wretch. Did not he with the reſt of the Tribes, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.9. acknowledge their Intereſt in <hi>David?</hi> Did they not prove it, when they confeſs'd that he did deliver them out of the hands of their Enemies, and out of the hand of the <hi>Philiſtines?</hi> Had not <hi>David</hi> been heartily concern'd in your Safety and Welfare, had you not had a near place in his Royal Heart, would he for your ſakes have courted Dangers, have carried his life in his hand, and have thruſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf amongſt bloody and perfidious Enemies?</p>
            <p>But how notorious will this Lye appear, when we look upon the 43d. Verſe of this Chapter, where it is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51468:6"/>ſaid by theſe very Men, <hi>We have ten parts in the King, and have alſo more Right in David than you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may be deſirous to know what might be the Deſign of this loud Lye; for few raiſe Lyes againſt their Sovereigns barely for lying ſake; but they have ſome farther wicked end to ſerve. <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Deſign was this: He ſaw that he and his Tribe had put a bar in the way of their Preferment, both by Rebelling againſt <hi>David,</hi> and alſo in being tardy to bring the King back after that Rebellion was ſo happily appeaſed; and thence he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, it was vain for him or them to hope for any great Favours; for if <hi>David</hi> had none of their hands, it was unreaſonable to expect they ſhould have any of his Countenance. Princes do not uſe to be ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in the diſtribution of their Rewards, as to heap Honours upon thoſe that ſought to prevent their juſt Rights, or that impair their juſt Titles; though in this Age this Rule hath been broke for the ſake of ſome. Being thus conſcious of his own Demerits, <hi>Sheba</hi> ſought to embroil the Nation, perſuading to a general Defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inſtead of a National Aſſociation.</p>
            <p>The next thing unſeemly and worthy Reproof in this ſhort Speech is the Slander and Contempt, in theſe Words, the Son of <hi>Jeſſe.</hi> He upbraided <hi>David</hi> with his Deſcent and Family, calling him the Son of <hi>Jeſſe,</hi> whom he ought to have honoured with the Title of King, This was done in ſcorn; and thus ſome of our ſaucy ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverent <hi>Sheba</hi>'s call him only Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> whom they ought to acknowledge as rightful King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls thoſe that ſpeak contemptuouſly of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, filthy Dreamers, Perſons whoſe Words declare that their Wits and Senſes have been aſleep, while God hath brought about this Revolution.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:51468:6"/>
Such another Son of <hi>Balial</hi> was <hi>Nabal;</hi> but how ſhall. <hi>Sheba</hi> or <hi>Nabal</hi> excuſe themſelves, if ever it enters into their hearts to conſider that he whom they ſpeak thus contemptouſly off, and ſet at naught, is no leſs than the Lords Anointed?</p>
            <p>He is a Traitor to his Prince who ſlanders and reviles him, though not ſo great a Traitor as he that conſpires againſt his Life, Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>The next Particular is the Treaſon: <hi>Every man to his Tents O Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Conſequence of which Words, was to perſwade the greateſt part of the Kingdom to Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; which once effected, he hoped that the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> for fear or ſhame would have come over to them; and then peradventure he himſelf might get into the Throne; (as being of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Family) or otherwiſe a Commonwealth might follow thereupon, wherein it was more eaſie for him to put in for a ſhare in the Government. For this you may obſerve, that there are but few Plotters or Conſpirators but what are Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous or Ambitious.</p>
            <p>This was a Speech indeed, and very ill becoming the mouth of a <hi>Jew;</hi> yet I could match it, and out do it, with one ſpoken by a reputed Chriſtian, who may well hide his Head (as he now doth) had he nothing more than a Black-mouth to anſwer for.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be God the Lot is fallen to us very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, and we have a goodly Inheritance in our <hi>David</hi> a large Inheritance of Piety, Wiſdom, Juſtice, Goodneſs, and Valour, God give us the grace unanimouſly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend this our Inheritance.</p>
            <p>This Speech thus taken in peices expos'd and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, I will now ſhew you how unreaſonable this <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamite</hi> was in this Invective againſt <hi>David,</hi> and that he really had no cauſe to quarrel with that Revolution
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51468:7"/>which Providence had made in the Throne of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and this I will do firſt by making ſome remarks on the Perſon remov'd, and next conſidering ſome things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in the Perſon placed in his room.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which might have quieted <hi>Sheba</hi> and his Tribe was, The Perſon Abdicated, <hi>viz. Saul</hi> was removed for his Diſobedience againſt the poſitive Commands of God.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures are ſilent, as concerning <hi>Saul</hi>'s be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour while a private perſon, and if we may ſuppoſe him them tractable and obedient, his new Honour made a wonderful Alteration, but ſome have got ſo much King-craft, that they can diſguiſe their natural Tempers, and diſſemble better, till ſuch time as they judge they may diſcloſe their own without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul. For, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.1. he was anointed; V. 8. he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives command by the ſame hand that anointed him, to go down to <hi>Gilgal,</hi> and there ſtay ſeven days, where <hi>Samuel</hi> would come down and offer Burnt-offerings, Sacrifice, and Sacrifices of Peace-offerings, and ſhew him what he ſhall do; notwithſtanding this Order and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Saul</hi> fearing the Approach of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes upon an Office to which he was not call'd; he will ſtay no longer, but turn Prieſt and offer Sacrifice: obſerve, as light a matter as he counted it, <hi>Samuel</hi> tells him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.13. that it was a fooliſh Act, and he had thereby broken the Commandment of the Lord: His fear of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> could not juſtifie his diſtruſt of God's help, nor would the Devotion of his Sacrifice atone for the breach of God's Command: He ſhould have been as zealous to obey, as willing to be Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>It is great fondneſs to believe that God, who requires Obedience from thoſe of low degree, ſhould hold ſuch excuſed whom he hath placed in the moſt eminent Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51468:7"/>God's Rule of Exſpectance bears proportion to to the meaſure of his Liberality; and conſequently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Act of Diſobedience in ſuch Perſonages appears the more heinous, even from the greatneſs of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to which they are exalted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi>'s Charge was, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. to deſtroy <hi>Amalek.</hi> I confeſs the Tenour of the Commiſſion might ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing terrifie him, becauſe it was ſo general; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Age, Sex, Degree, or Quality, Man or Beaſt was excepted; yet ought he not ſo long to have pondered the thing in hand, as to forget his Obligation; if Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture repreſented his Obedience as cruel and ſanguine, Grace ſhould have reminded him of His uncontroulable Authority, who had given him this in charge; and then he had ſoon underſtood the greateſt Cruelty would have been to himſelf in ſuſpending the Execution. However <hi>Saul</hi> wanted not other Arguments to have ſatisfy'd the Relentings of Nature, as, that they were groſs Idolaters; and moreover, as God was pleas'd to acquaint him, they had deilt very barbarouſly when time was with <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and therefore he ſhould have concluded, that ſeeing God's time of Vengeance was come, and that God had deputed him to that Office, he muſt by no means decline it, or be partial in the Execution: Peradventure Covetouſneſs might ſolicit in behalf of <hi>Agag,</hi> propounding a plentiful Ranſom. However he ſhould have conſider'd, it had been more happy to hear the Heathen confeſſing, <hi>Verily there is a righteous God that judgeth in the earth,</hi> than to hear his Subjects vaunting, There is a rich King that reigneth in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> It may be Hypocriſie became Advocate for the choiceſt of the Cattle, alledging if ever the Caſe were examined, it would be a ſufficient excuſe to plead they were ſpar'd for Sacrifice: But <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould rather have believed the Lord had not that Delight in Burnt-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51468:8"/>and Sacrifices, as in the obeying and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his Commands.</p>
            <p>Mercy is one of the brighteſt Jewels that can adorn a Prince's Crown; nay, it gives Beauty and Luſtre to the reſt; but to ſpare Idolaters, God's profeſſed Enemies, to reſcue thoſe that God hath appointed to dye deſerves not ſo good a Name; and they that preſuming on their Power will adventure on ſuch Indulgence, muſt expect to fare no better than <hi>Saul</hi> did; who, for ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable fondneſs, in oppoſition to God's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands forfeited both his Kingdom and his Life; for therefore God rejected him, as is apparent, V. 26 of that Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Advice is therefore as proper for Crowned Heads as for the meaneſt of their Subjects: <hi>The Fear</hi> of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom; then do Princes begin to grow wiſe and politick, when they grow fearful of violating the leaſt of God's Commands; a Rule that all who would eſtabliſh their Thrones muſt make Conſcience of obſerving.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sheba</hi> and his Company might have been ſatisfied in the Providence of God's depoſing <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe they well knew <hi>Saul</hi> was falſe and inconſtant to his moſt ſolemn Oaths and Engagements.</p>
            <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Gibeon,</hi> by crafty Pretences, drew <hi>Joſhua</hi> into Covenant, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.15. however <hi>Joſhua</hi> moſt religiouſly obſerv'd the Articles he made with them: He knew they did ill to make Lies their Refuge; but yet he foreſaw he ſhould do much worſe if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from his Promiſe; and this Covenant, though fraudulently obtain'd, was for many Ages punctually maintain'd. Surely then, that Prince (according to this Rule and Preſident) cannot be properly term'd juſt, who maketh no Conſcience of ſuch ſolemn En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements, as he is led to by his Coronation-Oath and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51468:8"/>the Principles of Honour and Equity. Theſe <hi>Gibeonites</hi> liv'd ſafely and happily for many Years under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s and the Princes of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, till ſuch time as King <hi>Saul</hi> over exalted by Reflections on his own Power and Greatneſs, ſcorn'd to pay any farther deference to that Ancient and long eſtabliſhed Chariter; but to curry favour with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, inhumanly ſlew Multitudes of thoſe poor Wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, notwithſtanding they were now become Members of the true Church.</p>
            <p>It is ridiculous Flattery to inſtill into the Ears of Prince, that they are ſuperiour to the Obligations of their Vows, Grants, and Promiſes, and it is as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Truth of Chriſtianity to perſwade them that any earthly Power can diſpenſe with, abrogate, or diſanull ſuch ſacred and ſolemn Engagements as they at any time make from their Thrones unto their People.</p>
            <p>Such as pretend otherwiſe, would acquit themſelves more honourably would they tell the World that the Ceremonies of a Coronation-Oath once perform'd, there remains no farther Obligation on the Crowned Perſon to be Juſt and Faithful: Had ſuch plain Dealing been uſed when time was, the Diſpute about the Succeſſion had found many leſs Advocates than it did.</p>
            <p>To return to the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> and from God's Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating <hi>Saul</hi> therewith conſidered, we may obſerve, that when ever they who in the honeſty and ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their hearts, rely'd on the Honour and Faith of Solemn Promiſes, were by their too eaſie credulity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, and thereupon appealed unto the unerring Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Almighty, they conſtantly found relief: It was likely their Addreſſes were kept, or thrown out of the Courts of ſuch violent Princes; yet their bitter Cries and their innocent Blood pierced the Heavens; and he with whom there is no variableneſs, nor ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51468:9"/>of turning, was very ready to revenge ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varications. Others, beſides <hi>Saul,</hi> may ſubſcribe to the Truth of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> had done juſtly, and what became him, to have left the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> in the ſame ſtate he found them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his coming to the Crown: He lay under no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to vex or ſlay them; they had lived loyally and therefore eaſily under former Governments, and would have done the like under his.</p>
            <p>If Princes, to ſhew the Mightineſs of their Power ſhall unjuſtly invade the Liberties, Lives, Rights, and Privileges of their Subjects, (for ſecurity whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Ancient Grant of Bountiful Kings, they have the ſtanding Laws of the Kingdom) they can expect no other than that God ſhould ariſe, and take the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his own hand, and deliver the Afflicted out of the hands of ſuch unrighteous and cruel Judges. Thus he appear'd for the wrong'd <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> and thus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably (bleſſed be his name) he hath alſo appeared for us of theſe Nations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sheba</hi> and his Crew might have reſted better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the Providence of God depoſing <hi>Saul,</hi> becauſe they were not ignorant that <hi>Saul</hi> was cruel and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, and mightily abuſed his Power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> entered upon his Government in a ſmooth and winning way, and is ſaid, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13 1. to have reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two Years; that is, the firſt two Years he governed with Juſtice, Prudence, and Love, according to the eſtabliſhed Laws of the Kingdom; but the reſt, in which he gave way to his arbitrary Power and Paſſion, are not recorded.</p>
            <p>I confeſs theſe Words, <hi>He reigned two years,</hi> will admit another Conſtruction; but I know not whether the looſeneſs of the Times will bear ſuch ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: However this it is; <hi>Saul</hi> reigned two Years
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51468:9"/>well, and ſo reigned rightfully; but though he kept the Throne ſome time after God rejected him, he was not accounted to reign as a lawful King, but as a Tyrant, holding Poſſeſſion till God drove him out. This Senſe ſome cannot away with; for they know no better, than if a King be crown'd it is no matter how he governs; for if once he hath got the Power into his hands, theſe Slaves ſay it is damnable to reſiſt him: And this ſtrange Doctrine they would fain build upon that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2. The genuine Interpretation of which Place is certainly this; Power is the Ordinance of God; ſo, as that for the preſervation of Peace and Order in the World, God did ordain that ſome ſhould Command and others Obey, yet I think it cannot thence be concluded, that either God did preſcribe what particular Form or Manner of Government ſhould be uſed in every part of the World, as Monarchy, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracy, or Democracy; or, that he did prohibit the removing of any Perſon upon his Male Adminiſtration from either ſort of Government. Government being God's Ordinance, where a Form thereof is eſtabliſhed, for Diſaffected Perſons to reſiſt, or ſeek the Subverſion of ſuch Form, is reſiſting the Ordinance of God, and ſuch may expect to receive to themſelves Damnation: however, to apply this Rule to the Perſon governing would be dangerous, as, to ſay that a King of a Free People, who upon his Coronation ſtipulates with his People, and binds his Soul with an Oath to Govern according to the Laws of the Kingdom, may, if he be ſo minded, Rule without Limitation or Reſtriction, and may not be Reſiſted in, nor Depoſed for ſuch Tyranny; for hereupon not only would Confuſion follow (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent which Government was ordain'd) but the Perſon ſo abuſing his Power muſt be allow'd to be the Ordinance of God: and then many times we ſhould find the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51468:10"/>of God thwarting, oppoſing, and beating down the Will of God, which is his own Glory, and the well governing of his People. At this rate God might be thought (were it not abominable ſo to imagine) to have eſtabliſhed Wickedneſs by a Law, and to be the Author of all the Injuſtice, Cruelty, and Barbarity, committed by Evil Men in Authority. All Power that acteth agreeably to God's Law is moſt properly of God; but that God alloweth of no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant employing Power, we may find he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a Prerogative of calling them that ſhall be guilty of ſo doing to an Account for that Power; for <hi>Dan.</hi> 425. <hi>God ruleth in the Kingdoms of men, and giveth them to whomſoever he pleaſes:</hi> That we may believe this, we find it repeated Ver. 32. And to put the matter beyond all doubt, in the ſame place we find a Preſident; for Ver. 33. the ſame hour this was fulfilled upon the great <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> whom by reaſon he had abus'd his Power in Pride and Luxury, God dethron'd. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that it belongs to God thus to deal with Crown'd Heads, look into Ver. 34. when by a ſeven Years Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was reformed, God reſtor'd him to his Throne. But now as pleaſing as this part of the Hiſtory may be to ſome, I deſire them to mark this alſo, That when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was dethron'd. God foreſeeing he would be reclaim'd, reſerv'd his Throne vacant, and his Diadem untouch'd, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſays, <hi>nemine audente toto ſeptennio invadere Dominium,</hi> none daring to take the Government during his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. Had God foreſeen the like in him he laſt Depos'd and turn'd to Graſs, to Herd with Beaſts, he had not fill'd the Throne with another. Crowns and Seepters are Gifts too great to be diſpos'd by any other hands than God's. And when we ſee a Good and Righteous Prince in Poſſeſſion, we have no reaſon to fear or doubt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51468:10"/>that God beſtow'd them on him. I ſpeak not of Poſſeſſion in that Senſe that ſome have done, curtailing the King's Right, and thereby encouraging ſome weak ones to think reſiſting him no Sir; for his Claim is much greater, in that the Gift that God gave him is moſt thankfully and joyfully confirmed, by our Laws, by the Aſſent, and Conſent, Hearts as well as Hands, of his People.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Saul</hi> was guilty of Oppreſſion and Cruelty, and mightily abus'd his Power, we need uſe no other Evidence than that we find upon Record 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.11. and onwards. I confeſs, I might have inſtanc'd in his raſh condemning <hi>Jonathan</hi> to Death, in his bloody Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of ſo many of God's Prieſts at <hi>Nob,</hi> upon the bare Information of a Muleteer or Aſs-Driver; his Heart was too tender to ſlay a ſingle <hi>Amalakite,</hi> an Idolater, yet he could command and behold the Slanghter of fourſcore Prieſts, beſides a mixt multitude of Women, Children, and Sucklings: but I ſhall keep only to the forecited Inſtance, and there we ſhall find proof ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Samuel</hi> propheſy'd of him, That he ſhould ſpoil his People of their Lands and Poſſeſſions, nay of their Sons and Daughters, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It was propheſy'd of him, That he ſhould take theſe things not for the Neceſſity of the Crown, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Country and Subjects, but to pleaſe his Pride, and to ingratiate with his Favourites.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Samuel</hi> propheſy'd of <hi>Saul,</hi> as you will find Ver. 16, 17. that he ſhould uſe his People more like Slaves and Vaſſals, than like a Free People, or God's Heritage: That this was foretold of <hi>Saul,</hi> the 18 Ver. makes appear, where it is ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall cry out in that day becauſe of your King which ye ſhall have choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Fancy or Good will could theſe People have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51468:11"/>for a King of whom they had received ſo terrible an Account by God's holy Prophet? yet read Ver. 19. <hi>all this moved them not, but they perſiſted, ſaying, but we will have a King.</hi> Who could have thought the <hi>Jews</hi> to be ſo ſtupid and ſenſeleſs! Yet we have heard others that match them, crying out, we will have a King, we will have the Crown deſcend in the Right Line, notwithſtanding more dangerous Circumſtances (than theſe foretold of <hi>Saul</hi>) were notoriouſly apparent in the Succeſſour. But what ſhall we ſay! ſome are yet madder than <hi>Jews,</hi> and they are ſuch, who once groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under <hi>Saul</hi>'s Perſecution, and yet when God who had puniſhed them by granting their deſire, was pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to relieve them; for he did, as is ſaid <hi>Hoſea</hi> 13.11. <hi>gave them a King in his anger, and took him away in his wrath.</hi> Inſtead of ſaying, <hi>the Lord gave and the Lord hath taken away, and bleſſed be the name of the Lord,</hi> we hear them blowing their Trumpets with Traitor <hi>Sheba,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>we have no part in David, nor inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in the Son of Jeſſe.</hi> Thus much of the Perſon Rejected; turn we now our Eyes to the Perſon Elected: His Name was <hi>David,</hi> or Beloved; he was indeed endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch wonderful Abilities and Perfections as were ſufficient to conciliate the Love of all but Monſters. Much I need not ſpeak, for the Scripture is every where ſo plentiful in his Commendation; however, you may take notice, that you may the better judge of <hi>Sheba</hi>'s unworthy Deſertion, 1. That this King <hi>David,</hi> of whom <hi>Sheba</hi> and his wicked Crew was ſo weary, was a King of God's chuſing. The People choſe <hi>Saul,</hi> as you read 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.18. for have <hi>Saul</hi> they would, though fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn'd of his ill Qualities; but God choſe <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.12. <hi>When David appeared, the Lord ſaid unto Samuel, ariſe, anoint him, for this is he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſo readeth the firſt Verſe of that Chapter, will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51468:11"/>find <hi>Samuel</hi> ſomething loth to go upon the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Anointing a new King; but he was not ſo backward but God was as urgent, asking him, How long wilt thou mourn for <hi>Saul: Samuel</hi> mourned not for <hi>Saul</hi>'s Depoſition, but Impenitence; otherwiſe he had ſhewed himſelf diſcontented with what God had done, (which be it far from us to imagine); however, we may ſee God likes not too much Lamenting the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he had Rejected how then would he have taken it if <hi>Samuel</hi> had made any Attempts to reſtore ſuch an one? I ſhould have thought, if the Troop of Non-Jurors had drawn up againſt this Text, they would have been utterly routed; but they never diſcover'd this Enemy.</p>
            <p>We cannot now expect that God ſhould give ſuch plain and poſitive Directions as formerly in the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Kings; yet are we not left without all Rule: for ſurely when we ſee unconceivable Hindrances remov'd, when we ſee that all that Force, Wit, and Power can do, miraculouſly diſappointed, and that the way to the Throne (as inacceſſible as it was thought) made ſmooth and eaſie, without Blood, Treachery, or Cruelty, what can we ſay leſs than that God hath done all this in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his Choſen?</p>
            <p>In plain terms, we are taught by our Religion to aſcribe all good Things to God, becauſe every good Gift cometh from him: Who then dare ſay, this is not a good and a great Gift that God hath given us, <hi>viz.</hi> a Wiſe and Valiant Prince, and with him a new Leaſe, (and I hope a very long one) of our Religion, Laws, and Liberties.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Particular manifeſting <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Complaint to be unjuſt, and the alienating <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Hearts from <hi>David</hi> to be traiterous, is, <hi>David</hi> was not only choſen of God, but he was the better of the two. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.28. <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Saul,</hi> that God had not only rent the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51468:12"/>from him, but that he had given it to a Neighbour of his, who was better than him.</p>
            <p>I cannot but take notice of this pious Courage in God's Prieſt, he was neither Son of Fear, nor Slave of Flattery; he could not call a wicked <hi>Saul,</hi> a moſt gracious and Religious King, but he told him that God had choſen a better; not that <hi>David</hi> was ſo much <hi>Saul</hi>'s Better by Nature, as Grace; for God had given him a better Spirit, more obedient and ready to do the Will of God, and ſet forth his Glory in Governing of the People committed to his charge, in Godlineſs, Peace, and Wealth.</p>
            <p>So much did <hi>David</hi> excell <hi>Saul,</hi> that he is ſaid to be <hi>a man after Gods own Heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Sermon at <hi>Antioch,</hi> 13. <hi>Acts</hi> 22. adds, <hi>which ſhall fulfill all thy Will.</hi> Hence it is eaſie to know who is the King of God's Election, or the King after God's own Heart; namely, he that delighteth in doing the Will of God, he that upholdeth true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtice, and Honeſty, in his Dominions; which are agreeable to the Will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> was really much better than <hi>Saul,</hi> not ſo much in regard of his extraordinary Endowments, as his gracious Performances; we find 78 <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. he fed God's People according to the Integrity of his heart; he gave them not Stones for Bread; he guided them by the skilfulneſs of his hands; he provided faithfully for his Subjects, he guided them by the beſt of Counſel, and defended them by the utmoſt of his Power; he neither ſold nor betray'd them; he neither enſlav'd nor impoveriſh'd them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.15. he executed Judgment and Juſtice unto all his People; ſo that there was no crying out nor complaining for want of Juſtice in the Streets of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:51468:12"/>
Before <hi>David</hi>'s time Religion was unſettled, the Ark was always ſhifting from place to place; but by <hi>David</hi> it was ſettled at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Surely it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Happineſs, and ſuch as may render a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bleſſed and acceptable, to have Religion ſettled, that we halt not between two Opinions, being in ſome places permitted to worſhip God, and in others called to adore <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s Calves.</p>
            <p>We read indeed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.11. of ſome Princes that accounted their chief Cities as Cauldrons, and their People as Fleſh to be ſod therein: Unhappy the People that are in ſuch a Caſe: and yet the time was, our City was a Furnace, and heated ſufficiently, to conſume the Inhabitants as well as their Goods and Houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jezabel</hi> had no other Opinion of Kingly Power, than that it gave the Poſſeſſor a free liberty of doing what he would, right or wrong: and therefore when <hi>Ahab</hi> made a Conſcience of taking away <hi>Nabal</hi>'s Vineyard, ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted him ſaying 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.7. <hi>Doſt thou now govern the Kingdom of Iſrael?</hi> I fear ſhe was not the laſt Queen that tempted a King to the Abuſe of his Power.</p>
            <p>Who can believe that God will ever permit his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be turned upon himſelf? and ſuch Princes as will by force turn out the True Religion to ſet up Idolatry, do nothing leſs than by their pretended <hi>Jure Divino</hi> abrogate God's <hi>Jura Divina:</hi> they make uſe of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God to beat down the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> far ſurpaſſed <hi>Saul,</hi> in that he Ruled well and in the Fear of God; for the Word ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. that <hi>ſuch are worthy of double Honour.</hi> And leſt ſome ſhould ſay, the People take too much upon them when they preſume to judge whether their Kings and Princes Rule well; to this it may be anſwered, Let the Laws of God and the Laws of the Land determine this Point. If they approve the manner of Governing, it is well, let
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51468:13"/>the People ſay what they will; but if they condemn it, it it ill, let Flatterers ſay what they pleaſe, or can.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sheba</hi>'s Uneaſineſs under <hi>David</hi>'s Government, and his Plotting and Conſpiring againſt him, is more unreaſonable, in that <hi>David</hi> had the Bleſſing of God upon his Reign, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.14. <hi>The Lord proſpered Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid whitherſoever he went.</hi> He gave him a ſtrong and courageous Heart to fear no Dangers; he gave him Skill and Strength of Arms to extricate himſelf out of them. God taught his Fingers to fight, and gave him Ability to break a Bow of Steel; to break the greateſt Strength of his Enemies: his Enemies either fled before him, or humbly crouched down to him; the Lord's hand was with him, and made whatever he did to proſper. God breathed upon his pious Undertakings, all things went on ſucceſsfully, Victory waited on his Sword, and Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on his Counſel. If his Enemies engag'd they were diſheart'ned; if they Plotted and Conſpired, they were by wonderful Providences detected and defeated. God bleſſed him at home, making his People willing and obedient; he bleſſed him abroad in giving him Honour among his Allies, and wonderfully covering his Head in the Day of Battel. Whether he went through the Water, or through the Fire, God went with him. In ſhort, he taught him to do ſuch wonderful things as the Kings of the Earth were aſtoniſhed to behold: it was eaſier with him to do them, than with them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them.</p>
            <p>To apply what hath been ſpoken,</p>
            <p>If I were now to ſpeak to you in the Words of the High-Prieſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.65. You have heard the whole Matter, you have heard <hi>Sheba</hi>'s double Blaſphemy, blaſpheming God and the King; for he that ſpeaketh againſt the Perſon choſen, ſpeaketh againſt him that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51468:13"/>choſe him likewiſe; now what think you? I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you would forthwith anſwer in the Words you find Ver. 66. <hi>He is verily guilty of Death.</hi> It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now time to tell you, the Caſe we are ſpeaking off is nearer you than the Land of <hi>Judea;</hi> it is come home to your own doors.</p>
            <p>Divers <hi>Sheba</hi>'s (ſeveral <hi>Jacobites</hi>) have long reviled and deſpiſed our Gracious Soveraign King <hi>William,</hi> and not fatisfied herewith, they are come to that height of Impudence, (Bluſh oh ye Heavens! Tremble O Earth! at the monſtrous Cowardice and Baſeneſs) encouraged by the Late King <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt his Life (which God defend.) Weigh what you have heard, and ſee if ſuch Conſpirators are fitting to live, or their Abettors to wear a Crown.</p>
            <p>Take therefore, I adviſe you, the wholſome and the expedient Counſel of <hi>Amaſa:</hi> And God grant that all of you may from the bottom of your Hearts Religiouſly promiſe to our King what he did to <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.18. <hi>Thine are we David, and on thy ſide thou ſon of Jeſſe; Peace, Peace, be unto thee, and Peace be to thy helpers, for thy God helpeth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I needed not to have ſet before you this Aſſociation of the Worthies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe you have ſo lately had the pious, glorious, and loyal Example of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> however you may hereby reap this Advantage, you ſee what theſe Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have now done, is no more than what God's Servants of old were wont to do, when God bleſſed them with a good King: To wit, to ſtand by him, own him, aſſiſt him, and defend him, againſt all Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, Uſurpers, Traitors, Conſpirators, and Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders whatſoever. Now if neither of both theſe confirm you in true Loyalty and Allegiance, how unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble will your Neutrality or Revolt be But I will ſpeak of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51468:14"/>no ſuch thing, becauſe I am ſatisfied you have been better taught.</p>
            <p>Yet I will take the liberty to ſound in your Ears a ſhort Alarum; if you are not in this juncture of time ſtanch, faithful, true, truſty and loyal, what will your Enemies conclude otherwiſe of you, than that your denying to ſtand by your King, is a giving them your Conſent and leave to extirpate your Religion? And can you call your ſelves Chriſtians, and give them the leaſt occaſion to think ſo? If you will not Aſſociate and Join in the Defence of your King, your refuſal is a ſounding of <hi>Sheba's</hi> Trumpet, and a calling the Enemy on to bind your gracious King with Chains, and your Princes and Nobles with Links of Iron; nay, to aſſaſſinate the one, and to murder the other; and can you with patience behold ſuch dreadful Spectacles? If you draw back, and will not Aſſociate, your Laws will be ſubverted, and what Pretender to Honeſty would live to ſee that Day! Your Liberties will be enſlav'd, and can an Engliſh Spirit brook this! Your Country a happy, rich, pleaſant, and fertile Soil, will be harraſſed with Fire and Sword, what Heathen would endure it! Your Wives and Children muſt be abuſed, rifled, raviſhed, and after all murdered, and who can live when all theſe things come to paſs? Let therefore theſe Conſiderations unite, confirm, and eſtabliſh you in ſtanding by your gracious Sovereign King <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now a Word farther, becauſe I hear ſome raiſing an Objection againſt this my Counſel, by pretending it goes againſt their Conſcience to join in the preſent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation; for the Word Revenge is in it, and this they ſear is inconſiſtent with Chriſtianity. I read indeed that wicked <hi>Joab</hi> fled for Sanctuary to the Horns of the Altar; but that Place was too holy to protect a Wretch ſo bloody and ſo infamous; and pray what
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51468:14"/>Right have theſe Ruffians of the moſt Chriſtian King (falſly ſo call'd) to appeal to Chriſtianity, when they practice ſo little of it? However I readily agree that the Chriſtian Religion is irreconcileable to Revenge; but how? as it is the effect of Malice and Paſſion, but not as it is the Act of Juſtice; for did not our Religion allow of purſuing, and executing lawful Vengeance on bloody Villains and Aſſaſſines, it would rather prove a Refuge for all manner of Wickedneſs, than a Rule for Piety and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>However, let us conſider the Words of the Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at which ſome ſeem to ſtumble: They are theſe, as I am inform'd, <hi>We do hereby farther freely and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly oblige our ſelves to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nite, Aſſociate, and ſtand by each other in Revenging His Majeſty's violent untimely Death, upon His Majeſty's Enemies and their Adherents.</hi> I ſee nothing here that can amuſe any Man; for when a Lawful Parliament require the Subjects to aſſiſt them in purſuing and puniſhing the Villains that have mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered their Gracious Sovereign, if any draw back and and refuſe their beſt aſſiſtance, upon a ſcruple of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I ſhould much queſtion their Morality as well as Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>But have a little Patience, and hear the Truth; for what theſe <hi>Sheba's</hi> talk of is meer Sham and Trick. The main Point is, the Parliament are reſolved to act Faithfully and Loyally; and, as the Words of their Aſſociation expreſs, defend His Majeſty's Royal Perſon and Government; but in caſe, after all their Care and Vigilance, he ſhould fall by theſe incarnate Devils (which God for Chriſt Jeſus's ſake forbid) they will ſupport and defend the Succeſſion of the Crown, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an Act made in the firſt Year of the Reign of King <hi>William</hi> and the late Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> intituled an Act, declaring the Rights and Liberties of the Subject,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51468:15"/>and ſettling the Succeſſion of the Crown. This, this is that which galls theſe Perſons; for they ſee if their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Plot ſhould take effect, that there would ſtill be no hopes for the Abdicated King, or the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> to come to the Crown.</p>
            <p>That you may believe the thing is lawful to which that Heroick Example of the Parliament invites, and I exhort you, conſider in the Days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> there was an occaſion for an Aſſociation; for <hi>Papiſts</hi> have ever mortally hated a true Proteſtant Prince. Now the Words of that Aſſociation are theſe; <hi>We will, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our Lives purſue, as well by Force of Arms, as by all other means of Revenge, any manner of Perſons who ſhall attempt any thing that may harm Her Majesty's Royal Perſon; and that we will never deſiſt from all manner of forcible Purſuit againſt ſuch Perſons, to the utter Extermination of them, their Counſellors, Aiders and Abettors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who ever called in queſtion the Piety of thoſe renowned Patriots? And yet the Words of their Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation were by far ſeverer than thoſe of the preſent.</p>
            <p>Chriſtianity forbids Revenge to private Perſons; and the Reaſon is ſuch, have the Magiſtrate, and the Laws to Defend, Protect, and Right them: But when Kings are Aſſaſſinated, and Kingdoms over-turned, there is no Law left to right them; and therefore in ſuch Caſes, Force may and muſt be uſed.</p>
            <p>Had this horrid Conſpiracy been effected, how ſhould we have been righted? The <hi>French</hi> Laws would not, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould not have been regarded: When therefore all Laws are thus ſilenced and trampled on, there is no way to reduce Men to Reaſon, but by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſuffer what is proper for unreaſonable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51468:15"/>
In ſhort, the Papiſts and Jacobites once have cajol'd this Nation, and, by their blind Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, did prepare Men's Throats for the Knife; and now they are detected and caught in a moſt ſavage and barbarous Plot, they would tie up our hands, upon the pretence Chriſtianity allows not Revenge; but I hope you will conſider better, than to let ſuch preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſcare you from your Duty, if ever you ſhall by a lawful Power be thereunto call'd.</p>
            <p>I muſt give you one Caution farther to keep you in this good Mind, to which I hope you are come, <hi>viz.</hi> to face any Danger for God and your King; and that is, take heed of ſome ſort of Doctrines.</p>
            <p>I hear one of the Conſpirators doth bewail his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, in taking up on Truſt what ſome furious <hi>Sheba</hi>'s trumpeted to him out of their Pulpits. There are many peſtilent Doctrines brought in to ſerve a turn: You would do well to avoid them, that you may keep your Conſciences void of Offence. I will name ſome of them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Doctrine of <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and the Conſequent thereof, the Diſpenſing Power.</item>
               <item>2. The Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience, and its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, Non-Reſiſtance.</item>
               <item>3. The Doctrine that teacheth the Difference betwixt the Church of <hi>England</hi> and that of <hi>Rome</hi> is not great; and its Conſequence, That a <hi>Papiſt</hi> is better than a <hi>Diſſenter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. And Laſtly, Take care of the Doctrine of a King <hi>de facto;</hi> that the preſent King is only a King by Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Crown; whereas he is Rightful King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of the Land. Take the Apoſtle's Counſel 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16, 17. <hi>Shun theſe profane and vain Bablers, for they will increaſe unto more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51468:16"/>their words will eat as doth a canker;</hi> in the <hi>Greek</hi> a Gangreen: that is, If Men take not due care theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Doctrines will poiſon their Minds after the ſame manner as a Gangreen does infect the Body, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diffuſes it ſelf, over-running all the Parts, and ſeizes the Brain, and pierces into the very Bones, if it be not cured by ſpeedily cutting off the Part infected.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So Perſons led away with theſe Doctrines are reſtleſs, going up and down, compaſſing Sea and Land, to draw others into the ſame Condition; therefore avoid theſe, that Communication with them corrupt not your Good Manners. Though Men Know the Devil can transform himſelf into an Angel of Light, yet they dare not therefore venture upon a Familiary with him; ſo notwithſtanding, Rebels, Conſpirators, and Aſſaſſines, may wear the glorious Name of Proteſtants, yet are they not therefore to be truſted; for if ever their hoped time ſhall come, they will unmask, and to your utter Confuſion you ſhall feel the Claws they now ſhut up.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Our Diviſions upon the Score of the Revolution, though they had no real foundation have been very odious, and of dangerous conſequence; yet, as hitherto the Government hath forbore harſh and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Methods, and hath ſo far abſtain'd from Rigour, that it hath not done Juſtice to it ſelf nor Freinds, it muſt be confeſs'd Mens black Crimes have both deſerv'd and call'd for it, and that the Rules of our Chriſtianity would have Juſtify'd the inflicting thereof: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in lieu thereof, we have heard of nothing but Mercy and Patience; Mercy, in moſt willingly giving Credit and Protection to all, and great Favours to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that make the leaſt true ſtep of returning to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Duty; Patience, in waiting for ſuch as were more obſtinate to be converted; but either the God of this World hath blinded Mens Underſtanding,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51468:16"/>or his Inſtruments have ſo ſeared their Conſciences, that they deſpiſe theſe Pearls (too rich for ſuch Swine): and as if the infernal Spirits were once again entered into the Herd, nothing will ſerve but rending and tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in pieces the gracious hands that offer them.</p>
            <p>To hope by Preaching to correct thoſe that have imbib'd ſuch unſound Doctrines, is more than I dare pretend to; however, I have now endeavour'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them of better Minds from receiving Infection by their Examples and Principles, and that by modeſtly laying open ſome of thoſe many Evils which occaſion'd and drew on the great Revolution: not that ſuch a Subject is inviting, eſpecially to us who have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the Change to admire and enjoy; but that if I cannot Silence, I may ſhame the querulous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſy; if I cannot prevent Obloquy, Slanders, nor Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, yet I may diſcover to the World the Unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of them that ſo ſpeak and act; as alſo, of ſuch as take Pleaſure in them.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>God Save King</hi> WILLIAM, <hi>and let all the People ſay</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
